Finding Aid for Howard Y. McClusky Papers 1921-1982
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Howard Y. McClusky Papers 1921-1982
McClusky, Howard Y. (Howard Yale), 1890-1982.
Professor of community and adult education at the University of Michigan; correspondence, writings, teaching material, subject files relating in part to his university activities, the Adult Education Association, and the American Youth Commission; also photographs and sound tapes.
86986 Aa 2
13 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mrs. Howard Y. McClusky (donor no. 6940 ), and the University of Michigan Department of Adult and Continuing Education in various accession in 1983 and 1984.
The collection is open for research.
Howard Yale McClusky was one of America's foremost educators, known especially for his work in adult education as it applied to the organization and activities of small communities. McClusky was born on February 20, 1900, in Whitesboro, New York. He attended Blackburn Academy and in 1921 graduated from Park College in Missouri. McClusky received a doctorate in educational psychology from the University of Chicago in 1929.
Five years before completing his Ph.D., McClusky accepted a teaching position at the University of Michigan. Between becoming an instructor in 1924 and his retirement in 1970, he established and chaired the University's Department of Community and Adult Education (1948-1970) and received the Distinguished Faculty Achievement Award (1958). After his retirement, McClusky continued to teach for another 12 years as a professor emeritus.
Although McClusky was strongly identified with teaching and advising graduate students at the University of Michigan, his professional activities were not limited to the university. In 1940 he was appointed associate director of the American Youth Commission (a unit of the American Council on Education). When the Commission was eliminated in 1942, McClusky was made a section chief of the Civilian Mobilization Branch of the Office of Civilian Defense.
He founded and was the first president of the Adult Education Association (AEA) in 1951. Six years later he helped to organize the Commission of Professors of Adult Education, the AEA's most prolific subunit. McClusky co-chaired the Section on Aging for the 1971 White House Conference on Aging.
Interspersed with his other activities, McClusky taught as a visiting professor at more than 10 universities and served as consultant to many civic organizations and governmental panels. A prolific writer, he published well over 100 articles and books. More impressive, perhaps, he delivered over 430 speeches during his life.
McClusky viewed his own career as one of "bridge building" between adult education and the disciplines of educational psychology, adult psychology, sociology, and gerontology. His was also a career wedded to the concept of "community development"; he felt that "the curriculum of adult education consists most effectively in the problems of the community [and] in the activities of the community." He launched the statewide drive to organize community councils in the 1930s. These councils consisted of concerned citizens interested in cohesively addressing their communities' needs and goals through public participation. Under the aegis of the Department of Community and Adult Education, the councils met together in annual conferences to share ideas and learn new techniques of citizen involvement.
Just as important as McClusky's interdisciplinary approach to education and his insistence on putting education to work in and for communities and regions, was the "life span dimension" of his thinking and work. He initially taught courses on the mental hygiene of childhood and adolescence, then served on the American Youth Commission where he focused on the problem of older rural youth, went on to found a department of adult education, and moved gradually to become a pioneer in the field of educational gerontology. He thus was uniquely qualified to discuss the psychology and sociology of learning, having studied learning throughout the human lifespan. And he spoke with authority about the capacity and necessity for "lifelong learning."
McClusky himself continued to learn, work, and teach until the end of his life. Already seriously ill, he taught his last class on April 13, 1982 (H652: Current Issues in Educational Gerontology). He died on August 15, 1982.
The papers of Howard Yale McClusky span the years 1921 to 1982. They include correspondence, clippings, bibliographies, speaking notes, reports, teaching material, minutes, photographs, and sound tapes. The bulk of the-papers are the files he kept in his office in the Department of Community and Adult Education. Every important aspect of McClusky's professional career is documented. His non-professional interests--such as his work with religious groups--and his personal life are only lightly touched upon in the collection.
The arrangement has tried to respect the original order of the papers. However, in order to highlight McClusky's most important commitments, some material was removed from his "Topical File" and consolidated into separate series. Respecting original order meant, among other things, leaving correspondence scattered throughout the collection in different subject folders. Only loose letters or folders composed entirely of letters were grouped in the Correspondence series.
The papers have been divided into eleven series: Personal and Biographical; Correspondence; Writings; Teaching Materials; Department of Community and Adult Education; Adult Education Association; American Youth Commission; Topical File; Visual Materials; Sound tapes; and Miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Adult education.; Adult Education Association.; American Council on Education. American Youth Commission.; Community organization.; Education--United States.; McClusky, Howard Y. (Howard Yale), 1900-1982.; University of Michigan. Community Adult Education.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Education.
Subjects - Visual Material:
McClusky, Howard Y. (Howard Yale), 1900-1982.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Classrooms--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Sound recordings
Adult education--United States.; McClusky, Howard Y. (Howard Yale), 1900-1982.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Personal and Biographical 1922-1982
  This series contains enough information to write a good short professional biography of McClusky. The Curricula Vitae spans sixty years, and some include lists of selected speaking engagements as well as lists of positions held and of publications. The bibliography on gold paper is the most recent and complete, although even it is not exhaustive. The file titled Eulogies and Feature Biographical Articles contains a critical analysis of McClusky's contributions to the field of educational gerontology, as well as tributes from colleagues and students. The Clippings folders, most of which are dated, primarily reflect McClusky's extensive activities as a speaker but also his work with the Michigan Council of Churches, community councils, special commissions, and civic organizations. Clippings are sparse, however, for the 1970s, and are missing entirely for 1942-1946. While most of McClusky's diaries are still held by his family, entries for scattered dates are found in the collection. The folder of Memorabilia contains numerous awards and a brief eulogy for his mother.
  - Curricula Vitae, Autobiographical Sketches, Bibliographies (Box 1)
  - Eulogies and Feature Biographical Articles (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1920s-1970s
    - 1920s-1930s (Box 1)
    - 1940-1941 (Box 1)
    - 1947-1948 (Box 1)
    - 1948-1949 (Box 1)
    - 1950-1954 (Box 1)
    - 1956-1958 (Box 1)
    - 1959-1970s (Box 1)
    - Undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Diaries, 1922-1981, undated (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Notebook: Diary Entries and Jottings 1938-1939 (Box 1)
    - Logs of Daily Activities 1942, 1948, 1962 (Box 1)
    - School Papers 1923, undated (Box 1)
    - Memorabilia (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1921-1982
  The "Correspondence" series has both a Chronological and a Subject subseries. The subject folders are remnants of McClusky's own filing system; the folder headings do not necessarily indicate especially important subjects. As noted above, additional correspondence will be found in many folders throughout the collection. Most noteworthy is the correspondence in the "American Youth Commission" series, much of which is with colleagues at the University of Michigan. The Correspondence series contains the only material on McClusky's personal life, in the letters from the 1920s and 1930s. Included in this early correspondence are long letters to his parents during his stay in Europe, 1931-1933. Most of the letters from the late 1930s on are from colleagues and others with whom McClusky was professionally acquainted. There are many notes thanking McClusky for speeches delivered, workshops conducted, and courses taught (indeed, the number of glowing letters from students is perhaps unusual). The correspondence also includes substantive accounts of McClusky's activities and intellectual positions. There are many requests for information about McClusky's work in community development, educational gerontology, and other fields. Worth special note is the correspondence McClusky conducted with Professor Roger Hiemstra of Iowa State University from July through September, 1979. Hiemstra wished to write an extensive biography of McClusky, and McClusky conducted a brief "life review" through the mail.
  - Chronological
    - 1921-1929 (Box 2)
    - 1931-1934 (Box 2)
    - 1936 (Box 2)
    - 1937 (Box 2)
    - 1940-1945 (Box 2)
      include letters to his wife, Helen
    - 1946-1949 (Box 2)
    - 1950-1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960-1969 (Box 2)
    - 1970-1974 (Box 2)
    - 1975-1979 (Box 2)
    - 1980-1982 (Box 2)
    - 1982 (Box 2)
      Letters to his wife, following Howard McClusky's death
  - Subject
    - Adams, James P. (Provost) 1945-1950 (Box 2)
    - Antioch College 1948 (Box 2)
    - Cummings, Milton C. (HEW) 1964-1965 (Box 2)
    - Detroit Committee for Rehabilitation of Narcotic Addicts 1951-1952 (Box 2)
    - Detroit, Miscellaneous 1960-1961 (Box 2)
    - Edmonson, J.B. 1946-1951 (Box 2)
    - Handbook of Adult Education Series 1970-1976 (Box 2)
    - Long, Huey 1969-1971 (Box 2)
    - National Council for Churches of Christ 1950-1953 (Box 2)
    - Nebraska, Miscellaneous 1949-1952, 1960 (Box 2)
    - New York, miscellaneous 1950-1962, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - New Mexico, Miscellaneous 1950-1953, 1956 (Box 3)
    - New Jersey, Miscellaneous 1951-1952 (Box 3)
    - Ohio, Miscellaneous
      - 1947-1952 (Box 3)
      - 1953-1961 (Box 3)
    - U.S. War Department 1946-1947 (Box 3)
    - University of the State of New York 1961-1962 (Box 3)
    - Zinn, Roger 1940-1941 (Box 3)
- Writings 1935-1982
  This series is composed primarily of addresses --mostly the speaking notes for the addresses--delivered by McClusky from the 1930s to 1982. A few typed transcripts and summaries are included. Most of the notes are handwritten, with date and place noted. Also included in the series are copies of a few published Articles--either not included on the gold bibliography or published in relatively obscure journals. Notes and Jottings are primarily typescript fragments of ideas and ruminations. The Reports include consultant analyses of adult education projects, a handbook chapter on community development, and an analysis of youth centers for the Governors Youth Guidance Committee. The Miscellaneous folders hold short pieces which seem to have been neither commissioned nor published. There are many pieces on community and adult education. Among the other miscellaneous pieces are "Ways of Knowing the High School Pupil," "The Relative Prestige of U of M Alumni Will Decline," "Some Reflections on Being a College Trustee," "The Role of the Local Church," and "What Kind of Community Do We Want?" The most important of these miscellaneous writings, however, are those on the Theory of Margin, one of McClusky's most important contributions to the theoretical context of adult education. (McClusky also published several articles on the theory.)
  - Addresses
    - 1930s (Box 3)
    - 1940-1941 (Box 3)
    - 1942-1943 (Box 3)
    - 1944-1945 (Box 3)
    - 1946 (Box 3)
    - 1947-1949 (Box 3)
    - 1950-1954 (Box 3)
    - 1955-1956 (Box 3)
    - 1957-1958 (Box 3)
    - 1959 (Box 3)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 3)
    - 1962-1965 (Box 4)
    - 1966-1969 (Box 4)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 4)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 4)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 4)
    - 1976-1979 (Box 4)
    - 1980-1982 (Box 4)
    - Undated (Box 4)
  - Articles
    - A-T and untitled, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Notes and Jottings
    - Typescript (Box 5)
    - Handwritten (Box 5)
  - Reports
    - Adult Education (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Adult and Community Education (Box 5)
    - Theory of Margin (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
- Teaching materials (mostly notes) 1930s-1982
  Along with McClusky's teaching notes, this series includes scattered handouts, exams, and bibliographies. His courses, descriptions of which may be found in the School of Education Bulletin, cover the mental hygiene of adolescence, adult education, and educational gerontology. Although these handwritten, often fragmentary, notes may not appear substantive or worthwhile, it remains true that McClusky was first and foremost a teacher, and that his students continuously testified to the compelling way in which he could translate these notes into a stimulating intellectual structure. At least a glance through this material is necessary for a thorough study of McClusky. The 1982 folder for H652 contains McClusky's thoughts on what he knew was the last class he would ever teach.
  - C120 (later C530): Mental Hygiene of (Childhood and) Adolescence
    - Notes
      - 1930s, 1940s (Box 5)
      - 1950s (Box 5)
      - 1960s (Box 5)
    - Handouts (Box 5)
    - Material Compiled by Students 1930-1931 (Box 5)
  - H282: Seminar in Community and Adult Education 1956, 1960, 1961 (Box 5)
  - H501: Survey of Adult and Continuing Education
    - 1978 and scattered earlier dates (Box 5)
    - 1979 (Box 5)
  - H510: Educational Gerontology
    - 1971-1978 (scattered) (Box 6)
    - 1979 (Box 6)
  - H652: Current Issues in Educational Gerontology
    - 1980, 1981 (Box 6)
    - 1982 include thoughts on teaching last class (Box 6)
      include thoughts on teaching last class
  - K680 (?): Individual Research in Education 1970 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Courses (Box 6)
- Department of Community And Adult Education 1938-1969
  The curriculum of community and adult education at the University of Michigan was the direct outgrowth of the "Program of Adult Education" established in 1938 by the Board of Regents and attached to the office of the vice-president in charge of university relations. In 1947 the program was expanded and assigned by the Regents to function as an integrated educational unit through the Bureau of Studies and Training in Adult Education the School of Education and the Community Adult Education Department of the Extension Service. In 1949 the Bureau of Studies and Training became Department H, Community and Adult Education, of the School of Education.
  The folder entitled "History and Purpose" contains extensive descriptions of the origins, development, programs, and philosophy of the department. The annual reports are also valuable in researching the history of the program. The memos, reports, proposals, and meetings folder contains some accounts of departmental activities during the 1940s and 1950s. Among the "Sound Tapes" at the end of the collection is a discussion of the department's problems and priorities.
  Most important of all the department's activities were the community councils; much information about them is contained in this series, with some additional material located in the "Photographs" and "Sound Tapes" series. The area conferences were used to stimulate interest in the expertise of community councils. Benton Harbor, St. Joseph, Centreville, Ida, Mason, Otsego, Sherwood, Vermontville, and Benzie County were subjects of the community surveys included here. The Michigan Community News permitted communities to share their development activities, and also reported on area conferences and the annual meetings of the community councils. The radio broadcasts are mostly transcripts of "The Awakening Community," broadcast over WJR and written by department staffers. Among the course material, the curriculum workshop was a week-long program "designed for mature workers in some phase of secondary education who are seeking something that is definite and helpful for improving the curriculum and instruction."
  - History and Administration
    - History and Purpose (Box 6)
    - Annual Reports 1938-1969, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Memos, Reports, Proposals, and Meetings (Box 6)
    - Staff Meetings and Staff Activities (Box 6)
    - Academic Programs and Course Descriptions (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Community Programs
    - Area Conferences for Community Self-Help (Box 6)
    - Community Councils
      - Descriptions, Histories, Bibliographies (Box 6)
      - Handbooks (Box 6)
      - Constitutions 1935-1947 (Box 6)
      - Conferences 1940-1955 (Box 7)
      - Directories 1944-1950 (Box 7)
      - Reports by Cynthia Jones 1948, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Community Forums 1939-1940 (Box 7)
    - Community Studies 1939-1942 (Box 7)
    - Community Survey Forms 1950-1957 (Box 7)
    - Michigan Community News
      - Typescript Articles (Box 7)
      - Newsletter 1939-1964 (Box 7)
    - Radio Broadcasts
      - 1939-1940 (Box 7)
      - 1941 (Box 7)
      - 1942 (Box 7)
      - 1943 (Box 7)
      - 1944 (Box 7)
      - 1945-1946 (Box 7)
    - Youth Centers (Box 7)
    - Robinson, William G.: Reports (Area Conferences, Community Council Conferences, Summer Institutes) 1947-1952 (Box 7)
  - Courses
    - Community Development Discussion Course (Box 8)
    - Curriculum Workshop
      - 1940 (Box 8)
      - 1941 (Box 8)
      - 1942 (Box 8)
      - 1943 (Box 8)
    - Experimental Correspondence Course, "The Community Looks at Itself," 1940 (Box 8)
    - Wednesday Night Discussion Group on Curriculum of Department (Students of H501) 1967-1968 (Box 8)
- Adult Education Association 1951-1982
  The Adult Education Association was founded by McClusky in 1951 to unify efforts in the field. Its purpose was "to further the concept of education as a process continuing through life" by educating adult educators and encouraging the development of adult education programs. The material in this series is primarily correspondence, although memos, reports, minutes, newsletters, speeches, and brochures also appear. The "First Annual Report" is a good introduction to the origins, purpose, and early activities of the association. McClusky, though president only for the AEA's first year, remained an important force in the organization.
  The Commission of Professors of Adult Education, a semi-autonomous unit of the AEA, was evidence of McClusky's continued involvement after his presidency. The Commission was initially funded by a W.K. Kellogg Foundation grant, and was charged with considering problems and issues associated with the development of graduate curricula in adult education. The Commission produced several important works, including the 1970 Handbook of Adult Education. The material here includes statements of purpose and objectives, proceedings of and reports to the annual meetings, memos, outlines, and notes.
  - National
    - 1951, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - 1952, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - 1953-1959 (Box 8)
    - 1960-1982 (Box 8)
    - 1971 Report by McClusky (Box 8)
  - Commission of Professors of Adult Education
    - 1957-1959, Undated (Box 9)
    - 1960 4th Annual Conference, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - 1961 (Box 9)
    - 1962 (Box 9)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 9)
  - Michigan 1952-1969
    - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
- American Youth Commission 1940-1942
  Established in 1935 as a unit of the American Council on Education, the commission was "concerned with the over-all organization of services for youth: private, local, governmental, state, and Federal." The commission investigated areas of need and the activities of extant agencies, then published reports and recommendations. As associate director for two years, McClusky was most intimately involved with the Rural Youth Project. The project conducted studies in Iowa, Virginia, and Michigan during McClusky's tenure. Material in this series includes reports, minutes, correspondence, notes, surveys, and memos relating to the activities of the commission as a whole and to-the Rural Youth Project in particular. (As noted elsewhere, much of the correspondence in this series is from McClusky's colleagues at the University of Michigan, discussing developments in the adult education program there.)
  - General (includes correspondence relating to U of M)
    - 1940 (Box 9)
    - 1941, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Advisory Committee of the Rural Youth Project
    - 1939-1940 (Box 9)
    - 1941, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - 1942 (Box 9)
    - Allegan County, Michigan, Project 1941 (Box 9)
    - Iowa
      - Dissemination Project 1940 (Box 9)
      - General Information, lists, etc. 1940-1942 (Box 9)
- Topical Files circa 1938-1978
  The headings are mostly names of organizations, but include some general subjects as well. The folders contain scattered correspondence, reports, notes, memos, minutes, brochures, and mass mailings. One document worth mentioning is in the Detroit Public Schools folder: a 1958 consultant's report by McClusky for the School-Community Relations Subcommittee of the Citizens Advisory Committee on School Needs. Also noteworthy, under the heading Adult Education, Michigan, is McClusky's 1959 workpaper on adult education, used to brief G. Mennen Williams at the Haven Hill Conference.
  - Adult Education
    - Michigan
      - Surveys and Reports 1944-1976, 2 folders (Box 10)
      - McClusky Workpaper for Governor Williams December 1959 (Box 10)
    - National 1958-1968 (Box 10)
    - General
      - 1938-1944 (Box 10)
      - 1948-1949 (Box 10)
      - 1950-1962 (Box 10)
  - American Association for Adult Education 1939-1950 (Box 10)
  - American Educational Research Association 1958-1959 (Box 10)
  - American Psychological Association 1947, 1960 (Box 10)
  - Appalachian Adult Basic Education 1969 (Box 10)
  - Citizenship Programs 1940 (Box 10)
  - Committee on Rural Education 1942 (Box 10)
  - Community Action Newsletter 1945-1946 (Box 10)
  - Community Activities
    - Addison 1939-1942 (Box 10)
    - Fenton 1939-1956, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Flint 1938-1943 (Box 10)
    - Hartland 1936-1952 (Box 10)
    - Upper Peninsula 1941 (Box 10)
    - Other Communities 1941-1944 (Box 10)
  - Community Organization 1938-1942 (Box 10)
  - Council for Research in Education 1963 (Box 10)
  - Detroit Public Schools 1950-1962 (Box 10)
  - Gerontology 1973-1978 (Box 11)
  - Group Dynamics 1952-1956 (Box 11)
  - Home-School Workshop 1952 (Box 11)
  - Kellogg Foundation 1938-1939 (Box 11)
  - Kelly, Governor Harry F. 1945-1946 (Box 11)
  - Leadership Training 1949-1959, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Mental Hygiene for High School Students 1948-1949 (Box 11)
  - Mott Foundation, Flint 1942-1960 (scattered) (Box 11)
  - National Association of Manufacturers 1954-1956 (Box 11)
  - National Association of Public School Educators 1958-1962 (Box 11)
  - National Commission for Adult Literacy 1958-1959 (Box 11)
  - National Community School Clinic 1959-1961 (Box 11)
  - National Conference on Family Life 1946-1947 (Box 11)
  - National Council for Community Improvement 1950-1956 (Box 11)